Noël A. Cazenave Papers
© 2005 University of Connecticut
Noël A. Cazenave Papers.
undated, 1988-1999.
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center.
Cazenave, Noël A.
1 linear foot.
Undergraduate work at Dillard University. M.A. from Michigan. Ph.D. from Tulane (1977). Temple University awarded tenure 1984. Most of research focuses on the impact of structured inequality on social identities, structures and processes.
MSS19990055
Biography
Noël A. Cazenave received is B.A. degree (Magnum cum Laude) from Dillard University in 1970. Cazenave continued his studies at the University of Michigan (M.A. Psychology, 1971) and Tulane University (Sociology, Ph.D., 1977). He was a professor of sociology at Temple University (Assistant Professor 1978-1984; Associate Professor 1984-1991) before accepting the position of Associate Professor of Sociology at the University of Connecticut. The author of numerous publications, Cazenave's current research interests include Poverty Policy, Racism and Political Sociology. A 1999 copy of his curriculum vitae is available, providing a complete list of publications, lectures and awards.
Scope and Content
The collection contains materials collected by Dr. Cazenave in his struggle to develop and teach a course on White Racism at the University of Connecticut. The course was first proposed as a Special Topics seminar in the Sociology department. After submission to the College of Liberal Arts and Sciences' Curricula and Courses Committee, the proposal was tabled twice before it was finally approved. In the interim, Dr. Cazenave turned to the media to garner support. After intense opposition, the Special Topics seminar was offered in 1996 and became a permanent course (graduate and undergraduate) a year later.
The collection contains correspondence, proposals and supporting materials, clippings, publications, notes, audio recordings and a video recording documenting the three-year struggle to have the course included in the curriculum of the University.
The materials have been arranged in an order to reflect the development of the conflict.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to the University, its history, administration, faculty, staff and students. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Index Terms
This record series is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Subjects:
University of Connecticut—Curricula.; Universities and colleges—Connecticut.; Poverty—United States.; Racism—United States.; Political sociology.; Universities and colleges—United States—Curricula.
Document Types:
Correspondence.; Personal Papers.; Manuscripts.; Publications.; Audio recording.; Video recording.; Computer disk.
Occupations:
Educator.
Restrictions on Access
Addresses and telephone numbers have been redacted by the donor. Duplication of the audio and video recordings is restricted.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to Archives & Special Collections by Dr. Cazenave in June 1999.
Detailed Description
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1988-1999
  - Biographical/Professional Materials, 1988-1998 (Box 1:, Folder 1)
  - Department Communications, 1995-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 2)
  - Special Topics Course Proposal College of Liberal Arts and Sciences (CLAS) (Box 1:, Folder 3)
    - Curricula and Courses Committee, 1996-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 4)
      - Minutes, 1996-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 5)
  - Sociology 298 Special Topics
    - Course Related Materials, 1994-1996 (Box 1:, Folder 6)
    - Syllabus, 1996 (Box 1:, Folder 7)
  - Course Proposal, 1996-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 8)
  - Sociology 236
    - Lecture Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 9)
    - Course Related Materials, undated, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 10)
    - Syllabus, 1999 (Box 1:, Folder 11)
  - Sociology 305
    - Lecture Notes, undated (Box 1:, Folder 12)
    - Syllabus, 1998 (Box 1:, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 14)
    - Congratulations, 1995-1997 (Box 1:, Folder 15)
    - Personal, 1995-1996 (Box 1:, Folder 16)
  - Clippings, 1995-1996 (Box 2:, Folder 17)
  - Media Notes, undated (Box 2:, Folder 18)
  - Op-Ed Essay, 199? (Box 2:, Folder 19)
  - University and Community Forums
    - Community Dialogue, 1996 (Box 2:, Folder 20)
    - Militant Denial Presentation, undated (Box 2:, Folder 21)
    - University Forums, 1996 (Box 2:, Folder 22)
  - National Conference on Race and Ethnicity in American Higher Education (NCORE), 1998-1999 (Box 2:, Folder 23)
  - Post Conflict Developments, undated (Box 2:, Folder 24)
  - Articles
    - Arguments Response, 1997 (Box 2:, Folder 25)
    - Background/Source documents, undated (Box 2:, Folder 26)
    - Critical/Supportive statements, undated (Box 2:, Folder 27)
    - Race and Society, 1999 (Box 2:, Folder 28)
      - Comments, undated (Box 2:, Folder 29)
    - Teaching Sociology, 1998 (Box 2:, Folder 30)